Inventory of the Cabell Family Papers 1693-1913, 1743-1823
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Cabell Family Papers, 1693-1913, 1743-1823.
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Mss. 65 C12
3,192 items.
Accounts, surveys and correspondence, chiefly 1743-1823, of members of the Cabell family of Albemarle and Amherst Counties, Virginia.
Dr. William Cabell,; Col. William Cabell,; William Cabell, Jr.,; Cabell Family.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Purchased: 3,192 items, 07/18/1941.
Biographical/Historical Information
There were three generations of William Cabells who were surveyors. Dr. William Cabell (1700-1774) was a physician and assistant surveyor of Goochland and Albemarle Counties, Virginia under Joshua Fry and William Mayo. His son William Cabell (1729/30-1798) was also assistant surveyor of Albemarle County and surveyor of Amherst County, Virginia. His son and the third William Cabell (b. 1759) was surveyor of Amherst County, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
Accounts, surveys and correspondence, chiefly 1743-1823, of members of the Cabell family of Albemarle and Amherst counties, Virginia. Includes accounts and land transactions, 1733-1754, of Dr. William Cabell (1700-1774) as well as letters written to him concerning medical treatment. Also includes accounts, surveys of Amherst County and correspondence with commission merchants of William Cabell (1729/30-1798); and surveyor's license and surveys of William Cabell (b. 1759).
Also includes correspondence, 1796-1820, of William H. Cabell (1772-1853); correspondence of William S. Crawford, clerk of Amherst County; and correspondence relating to the will of Patrick Henry, Jr. including a list of books purchased from the estate of Patrick Henry (1736-1799). Prominent correspondents in the collection include Joseph Carrington Cabell, John Marshall, Philip Norborne Nicholas, Wilson Cary Nicholas, Edmund Pendleton and Peyton Randolph.
There are manuscript volumes of the field survey books of Dr. William Cabell; entry survey books for Goochland and Albemarle Counties, and lists of court cases by William S. Crawford as well as surveys signed by Joshua Fry and surveying business conducted by the College of William and Mary.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into two series, 1. Papers, and 2. Manuscripts.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically by date.
Additional Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Hughes, Sarah S. Surveyors and Statesmen: Land Measuring in Colonial Virginia. Richmond, Va.: Virginia Surveyors Foundation and the Virginia Association of Surveyors, 1979.
Related Material
Letters, 1885-1890, from William Cabell, England, to Alexander Brown, are located in the Cabell-Brown Collection within the Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library.
Cabell-Brown Papers, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary. Cabell- Brown Papers, 1885-1890. 12 items. Collection number: Mss. Sm Coll Cabell-Brown
The letters of Alexander Brown have been separated into two inventories, located within Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, that are related to the Cabell Fmaily papers.
Alexander Brown Papers (I), 1815-1910, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary. Alexander Brown Papers, 1815-1910. 2,949 items. Mss. Acc. 65 B83
Alexander Brown Papers (II), 1748-1900, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary. Alexander Brown Papers (II), 1748-1900. 1,434 items. Collection number: Mss. 65 B86
Index Terms
Family Names:
Cabell Family.
Persons:
Cabell, William, 1700-1774.; Cabell, William, b. 1759.; Cabell, William, 1730-1798.; Cabell, William H., 1772-1853.; Cabell, Joseph C. (Joseph Carrington), 1778-1856.; Crawford, William S., b. 1815.; Fry, Joshua, 1700 (ca.)-1754.; Marshall, John, 1755-1835.; Nicholas, Philip Norborne, 1775-1849.; Pendleton, Edmund, 1721-1803.; Randolph, Peyton, 1721-1775.
Subjects:
Medicine.; Henry, Patrick, 1736-1799.; Henry, Patrick, 1783-1804.
Corporate Names:
College of William and Mary--History--18th century.
Geographical Names:
Albemarle County (Va.)--History.; Amherst County (Va.)--History.; Goochland County (Va.)--History.
Occupations:
Surveying--Virginia--History.
Components List
  Series 1: Papers
- Papers, 1693-1913, n.d. (Box 1-9)
  - Receipt, 9 Oct. 1693., DS. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Contains the mark of Richard Chivers.
  - Note requesting payment to Mr. George Forman from (?), 15 Oct., 1725. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Receipt of William Cabell on account of Henry Reynolds, signed by Robert Hughes, 21 Aug., 1733., ADS. (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Agreement between William Crawford and W[illia]m Cabell, 27 Xbr [Dec.] 1733., ADS. (Box-folder 1:3)
  - James Christian of St. Ann Parish & Albemarle County, Virginia is bound unto William Cabell for the sum of 198 pounds 7 shillings and one penny, 23 June 1735., ADS. (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Will of Samuel Meridith of Saint Paules Parish, Hanover County, Virginia, 3 Jan. 1739., DS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Will contains the legacies to sons Elisha and Samuel and daughter Ruth Jordan. Witnessed by Geo[rge] Morrell and Tho[ma]s Ballard Smith.
  - Three receipts of W[illia]m Cabell, signed by Benja[min] Robinson and E. Bennet, 1739., ADsS. (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Receipt of Mr. Caveall from Samuel Read, scale maker of London, 24 June 1740., AD. (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Arthur Hopkins of "Dear Friend," about his sending Westcote Buttons and staples for the Baggs, 11 Jan. 1741., ALS. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Order of the Council held at the Capitol, signed by Rob[er]t Staunton and John Blair, 6 May 1743., ADS. (Box-folder 1:8)
    It was held upon the petition of William Cabell, Sen[io]r, Joseph Cabell, John Cabell, and William Hopkins, leave is granted them to take up 6,000 acres in Goochland County on the branches of Blackwater Creek and bounded on Nicholas Davis' land to extend backward towards other rivers.
  - Promissory note of Rob[er]t Burton and Pleas[an]t Cocke payable to Sam[ue]l Allen, 30 July 1743., DS. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Request for survey, signed by James Neville, 1743., ADS. (Box-folder 1:8)
    Note added that "Entry made 1743 Joshua Fry".
  - William Cabell, Richard Burk, and John Mims enter an order of Council for 1600 acres of land beg[inning] at Samuel Burks, Jun[io]r, 5 Aug. 1743., AD. (Box-folder 1:8)
    William Cabell enters for 400 acres of land beginning at the fork of Ioes Creek, and 400 acres on both sides of Fendlys Creek.
  - Entries in Col. Mayo's book and entries with Col. Fry, 5 Aug. 1743., AD. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - [William Horsey?] to "Sr" [Capt. William Cabell, Albemarle County], 3 April 1744., AL. [signature clipped]. (Box-folder 1:9)
    Letter concerns sending John Row with 2 Negroes to "bent plantation."
  - Order of Governor's Council that W[illia]m Cabell be granted leave to survey 1200 acres in Goochland County, signed by N. Walthoe, 3 May 1744., ADS. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Entries of W[illia]m Cabell for land transactions, 5 Aug. 1743 and 17 Oct. 1744., AD. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - A receipt for Certificates Rights and patent fees of William Cabell, signed by W. Wagner, 25 Oct. 1744., ADS. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Order of Governor's Council, 6 May 1743., ADS. (Box-folder 1:9)
    Item states that William Cabell be granted leave to take up 1200 acres in Goochland on both sides of the Fluvanna River. Entered in Auditors Office by John Blair, 29 Oct. 1744.
  - Accounts of Capt. William Cabell, 1744., ADs. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Debts of Robert Kidd. signed by H. Wood, March 1744-May 1745., ADS. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Land survey for W[illia]m Miller of 50 acres on the south side of Rockfish River, 5 Feb. 1746., ADS. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Surveys, signed by W[illia]m Cabell and Joshua Fry, 23 Feb. 1746 and 5 March 1746., ADsS. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - List of debts due W[illia]m Cabell, Aug. 1746., D. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Statement of Matthew Jordain., D. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Indenture between Charles Burks [Birks] of Albemarle County and John Pleasant of Henrico County, 12 March 1746., ADS. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Land Survey for William Johnson, Albemarle Parish, signed by W[illia]m Cabell and Joshua Fry, 11 Feb. 1747., ADS. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Land survey for Bishup[sic] Toney, signed by W[illia]m Cabell and Joshua Fry, 20 May 1747., ADS. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Receipt for Bishop Toney's two surveys, signed by Tho[ma]s Everard, 9 June 1747., ADS. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Note requesting payment of Capt. William Cabell from Patrick Napier, 23 June 1747., AD. [signature clipped]. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Land Survey, 27 Nov. 1747., AD. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Note giving details of survey for Capt. Charles Lynch, signed by W[illia]m Cabell, 25 Nov. 1747., ADS. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Land survey of 2460 acres on the south branch of Rockfish River, signed by W[illia]m Cabell and Joshua Fry, 31 Dec. 1747., ADS. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Land surveys signed by Joshua Fry, surveyor, W[illia]m Cabell, asst. surveyor; and Tho[ma]s Turpin, asst. surveyor; and receipts signed by Tho[mas] Everard, 1748., ADsS. (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Land surveys in Albemarle signed by W[illia]m Cabell, asst. surveyor, and Joshua Fry, surveyor, and will of George Braxton of St. Stephens parish in King and Queen County, 10 Oct. 1749., ADsS. (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Land surveys signed by W[illia]m Cabell, asst. surveyor, and Joshua Fry, surveyor, note signed by Ben[jamin] Waller, 1750., ADsS and ANS. (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Deed of sale by which Peter Randolph sold Samuel Burk a half acre lot in the town of Westham, 5 Dec. 1750., ADS. (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Papers relating to surveying, including survey of land in Albemarle County, signed by Tho[ma]s Jefferson, asst. surv[eyor], and Joshua Fry, surveyor, 10 April 1751., ADsS. (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Receipts and surveys signed by Tho[ma]s Turpen, asst. surveyor, and Joshua Fry, surveyor, 1752., ADsS. (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Surveys signed by W[illia]m Cabell, asst. surveyor, and Joshua Fry, surveyor. Condition of obligation between Mathew Talbot, Clement Read and Charles Talbot and Cornelius Cargill, Robert Henry Dyer, William Caldwell, and Abraham Martin, 1753., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Surveys signed by Pet[er] Jefferson and W[illia]m Cabell and receipts signed by Benj[amin] Waller and Tho[ma]s Everard, 1754., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Receipts signed by James Lyle, Geo[rge] Gilmer, James Nevil, and John Reid and survey signed by J[oh]n Staples, asst. surveyor, 1755., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Receipts signed by Cha[rle]s Binns, Ja[me]s Nivel, Ben Waller, and John Nicholas, 1756., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Charge to the Grand Jury, May and Nov. 1757., ADs. (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Receipt signed by James Nevil and Ben Waller, 1757. (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Survey signed by J[oh]n Staples, 1757., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Receipts of W[illia]m Cabell, Jun[io]r, 1758., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Receipts of W[illia]m Cabell, J[unio]r, one signed by T. Everard, 1759., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Receipts and an account of Dr. William Cabell with Robert Munford, Clk., 1760., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Receipt of Col. William Cabell with Ingram & Co., 1761. (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Official statement from N. Walthoe, Williamsburg, Virginia to the Justices of Amherst County, approving the place for the County Court House to be established, providing it be built at the expense of the county, 30 June 1761., ADS. (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Account of William Cabell with John Harvie, 1761., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Business papers, 1762. (Box-folder 1:28)
  - Deed of Sam[ue]ll Meredith [sic.], 16 Dec. 1761., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:28)
    Admitted to court record, 7 Jan. 1762.
  - Letters from Alex[ande]r McCaul, Richmond, to Dr. William Cabell, about sending the supplies he had ordered and discussing the price of tobacco. ALsS. 3 June 1763 and 1 June 1763. (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Surveys and receipts, 1763., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Receipts and surveys of Col. William Cabell, 1764., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:30)
  - Account of Col. William Cabell with Alexander McCaul, 1764., ADS. (Box-folder 1:30)
  - A list of fees received for surveys in Amherst County by William Cabell, Jun[io]r, surveyor., ADS. (Box-folder 1:30)
  - [?] Lenevess to Dr. William Cabell, requesting medical treatment for his wife and describing her symptoms, 22 May 1765., ALS. (Box-folder 1:31)
  - Surveys and notes concerning surveys by W[illiam] Cabell, Jun[io]r, surveyor, 1765., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:31)
  - Receipts, 1765., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:31)
  - Letter from Joel Watkins, Prince Edward County, to Dr. William Cabell, requesting treatment and listing his wife's symptoms, 30 Oct. 1765., ALS. (Box-folder 1:31)
  - "Invoice of Sundries shipt by the John, Capt. J[oh]n Breakhill for Virginia on Account of Collo. William Cabell, Jun[io]r," Feb. 1766., ADS. (Box-folder 1:32)
  - Notes relating to surveying., ANs (Box-folder 1:32)
  - A list of fees rec[eive]d for surveys in Amherst County by William Cabell, J[u]n[ior], surveyor., AD. (Box-folder 1:32)
  - Legal notice signed by Peter Randolph, authorizing William Cabell, J[u]n[ior], to be Deputy Escheator for the counties of Albemarle, Amherst, Buckingham, and Bedford, 12 Dec. 1766., DS. (Box-folder 1:32)
  - "Invoice of Sundries shipt by the John, Capt. John Breakhill for Virginia on Account of Col. William Cabell Jun[io]r," 7 Feb. 1767., ADS. (Box-folder 1:33)
  - Receipts and surveys, 1767., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:33)
  - "A list of fees rec[eive]d for surveys in Amherst County by W[illia]m Cabell J[unio]r surv[eyo]r," Feb. 1768., ADS. (Box-folder 1:33)
  - "Invoice of Sundries shipt per the John, Capt. John Breakhill for Virginia on acco[un]t of Col. W[illia]m Cabell Jun[io]r," Feb. 1768., ADS. (Box-folder 1:34)
  - Receipts signed by Ben[jamin] Waller, James Nevil, 1768., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:34)
  - Richard Shelton to [Dr. William Cabell], about his daughter's illness, 28 Aug.1768., ALS. (Box-folder 1:34)
  - Survey signed by Ja[me]s Higginbotham, asst. surveyor, and W[illiam] Cabell, surveyor, 2 Dec. 1768., ADS. (Box-folder 1:34)
  - Receipts, 1769., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:35)
  - John Backhouse, Liverpoole, to Col. William Cabell, Jun[io]r, 1769., ADsS (Box-folder 1:35)
  - Account of William Cabell, Jun[io]r with the College of William and Mary, settled May 1769 (for 1768) "for the use of the College of William and Mary," signed by John Blair, Jun[io]r on the reverse of "A List of Fees Received for surveys in Amherst County by William Cabell Jun[io]r surveyor," May 1769., ADS. (Box-folder 1:36)
  - Settlement of the account of William Cabell, J[unio]r surveyor of Amherst with the College of William and Mary, "for the use of the College of William & Mary," signed by John Blair, on reverse of "A List of Fees Rec[eive]d for surveys in Amherst County by William Cabell, Jun[io]r, surveyor." 14 Nov. 1769., ADS. (Box-folder 1:36)
  - Receipt for callico and linen, etc. for Mrs. Cabell, 1769[?]., ADS. (Box-folder 1:37)
  - Receipts of Col. William Cabell, 1770., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:38)
  - "Sales of ten H[ogs]h[ea]ds Tobacco received Sept: 1769 per the John from Virginia on Account of Col. William Cabell Jun[io]r" and "Invoice of Sundries Shipt by John Backhouse on board the John J[oh]n Breakhill for Virginia on Acc[oun]t Col. Will[iam] Cabell Jun[io]r," Sept. 1769., ADS. (Box-folder 1:38)
  - John Backhouse, Liverpool, to Col. William Cabell, about his tobacco sales and invoice, 14 Feb. 1770., ALS. (Box-folder 1:38)
  - Surveying papers, 1770., ADSS. (Box-folder 1:38)
  - Ben[jamin] Howard to [Dr. William Cabell], about his wife's illness, 3 Aug. 1770., ALS. (Box-folder 1:38)
  - Account of William Cabell with the College of William and Mary, on reverse of "A List of Fees Received for surveys in Amherst County by William Cabell Jun[io]r, surv[eyor]," signed by Rob[er]t Miller, Bursar, 22 Oct. 1770., ADS. (Box-folder 1:38)
  - John Backhouse, Liverpool, to Col. William Cabell about the insurance due on the wheat and tobacco, 17 July 1770., ALS. (Box-folder 1:39)
  - "Invoice of Sundries Shipp[e]d by the John Capt J[oh]n Breakhill for Virginia on Account of Mr. William Cabell Jun[io]r.", ADS. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Receipts of William Cabell, Jun[io]r, 1771., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - John Backhouse, Liverpool, to William Cabell, Jun[io]r about his account, 1771., ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Surveys by Ja[me]s Higginbothan, asst. surveyor, and W[illiam] Cabell, Jun[io]r, surveyor, in Amherst Co., Va., 1771., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - "A List of Bonds & Cash delivered Peyton Randolph Esqr., Executor of the Will &c. of the Hon[ora]ble Philip Grymes Esqr. deed... .", AD. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Settlement with Peyton Randolph Esqr., Executor of the Will &c. of the Hon[ora]ble Philip Grymes Esqr. and Cr., signed by Peyton Randolph, 20 July 1771., ADS. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Peyton Randolph to Col. William Cabell, 6 Nov. 1771., Cy of ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Item concerns Thomas Lomax's giving security for his father's mortgage and removing the Negroes.
  - The accounts of William Cabell, Jun[ior] with the College of William and Mary, on the reverse of "A List of Fees Received for Surveys in Amherst County, by William Cabell Jun[io]r. surv[eyo]r," signed by Rob[ert] Miller, Bursar, 4 Nov. 1771., ADS. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - "Invoice of Sundries Shipp[e]d by the John Capt. John Breakhill for Virginia on Account of Coll. William Cabell.", ADS. (Box-folder 2:2)
  - John Backhouse, Liverpool, to Col. William Cabell, Jun[io]r, 4 Feb. 1772., ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Note about an account signed by G[eorge] Wythe, C.H.B. [Clerk of the House of Burgesses], April 1772., ADS. (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Edmund Pendleton to Col. William Cabell, 16 Sept. 1772., Cy of ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Item concerns his father's suit.
  - The account of William Cabell, J[unio]r, surveyor of Amherst Co. with the College of William and Mary, 15 Oct. 1772, on the reverse of "A List of Fees Rec[eive]d for surveys in Amherst County by William Cabell, jun[io]r, surv[eyor].", ADS. (Box-folder 2:2)
  - John Backhouse, Liverpool, to Col. William Cabell, Jun[io]r, 19 Feb. 1773., ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
    Item says "I am truly sorry they have not altogether answered your Expectations."
  - Surveys signed by Ja[me]s Higginbothan, asst. surveyor, and W[illiam] Cabell, Jun[io]r, surveyor, 1773., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:3)
  - W. Cabell, Amherst Co., to John Backhouse, 10 June 1773., ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
    States why he will not renew his consignment.
  - Legal papers, 1773., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Receipts and survey signed by Ja[me]s Higginbothan, asst. surveyor, and W[illiam] Cabell, surveyor, 1774., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Notes, receipts, and surveys signed by Ja[me]s Higginbotham, asst. surveyor and W[illiam] Cabell, surveyor, 1775., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Receipts and list of debts of Col. William Cabell in account with Charles Irving for Henderson & Company., ADs and ADsS. (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Account of William Cabell with William Loving, Dep[uty] Sheriff, Amherst Co., Virginia., ADS. (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Indenture between Edward Tinsley and Joshua Tinsley, 1 Aug. 1777., ADS. (Box-folder 2:7)
  - List of surveyors fees put into the hands of the sheriff of Amherst Co., 1778., ADS. (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Receipts, 1778., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Accounts, receipts, and notes, 1779., ADsS and ANsS. (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Accounts of Hampton Sydney Academy. 1778-1779., Cy[?] of AD. (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Land grant to William Aaron, signed by Thomas Jefferson, Governor of Virginia, 20 July 1780., D. Signature clipped. (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Accounts of Col. William Cabell, 1781., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Hugh Rose, Amherst, to Major William Cabell, 9 June 1781., ALS. (Box-folder 2:11)
    Item concerns getting arms as soon as the militia can assemble and asks Cabell to "sollicit all within your reach to turn out as volunteers to take the arms for a day or two until those ordered on duty can join... ."
  - Two lists of militia ordered into service from Amherst County, 1781., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Hugh Rose, Amherst, to Major William Cabell, 24 July 1781., ALS. (Box-folder 2:11)
    Item concerns Tarlton's march to the Court House.
  - Surveys signed by William Hay, asst. surveyor, 1782., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Surveys signed by Ja[me]s Barnett, asst. surveyor, and William Cabell, Jun[io]r, surveyor, 1782., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Receipts, 1782., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Surveyors license, issued by the College of William and Mary to William Cabell [William Cabell, Jr. (1759- )] and signed by James Madison, George Wythe, Charles Bellini, and Benjamin Harrison, 2 Oct. 1783., ADS. (Box-folder 2:13)
  - List of debts paid by Amherst Col, March 1783., ADS. (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Accounts and receipts, 1783., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Agreement between William Cabell and James Robards, 28 Feb. 1784., ALS. Oversize. (Box-folder 2:14)
    Includes house plans.
  - Accounts and receipts, 1784., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Debts paid by Amherst Co., 8 June 1784., ADS. (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Charles Crawford, Hampton Sydney College, to his brother William Sid Crawford, Amherst, 20 Jan. 1785., ALS. (Box-folder 2:15)
    About his studies.
  - Accounts and receipts, 1785., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:15)
  - A list of suits in which W[illia]m Crawford [attorney] is employed, Sept. 1785., D. (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Debts of William Cabell, J[unio]r, to the sheriff of Amherst, 18 Oct. 1773-16 Sept. 1785., ADS. (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Land grant to William Cabell, signed by Patrick Henry, 2 Dec. 1785., DS. (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Survey signed by Will[iam] Cabell, J[unio]r, surveyor, 1786., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Accounts and receipts, 1786., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:16)
  - A list of suits brought in the County Court of Albemarle by W[illia]m S. Crawford, [17]87., ADS. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Charge to the Grand Jury, unsigned, August 1787., D. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Surveys signed by Jos[eph] Barnett, asst. surveyor, and Will[iam] Cabell, surveyor., ADsS. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Legal document showing handwriting of Col. William Cabell, 1758 and 1788., ADS. (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Accounts and surveys of Amherst Co., signed by James Montgomery, asst. surveyor, and William Cabell, Jun[io]r, surveyor, 1788., ADsS. (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Accounts and legal papers of William Cabell, J[unio]r, 1789., ADsS. (Box-folder 3:3)
  - [Dr.] George Gilmer, Pen Park, to Col. William Cabell, 19 Dec. 1789., ALS. (Box-folder 3:3)
    Giving medical advice.
  - Two letters dealing with the levy to pay for the county gaol and repairing the court house, May 1790., ALsS. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Accounts of William Cabell, S[enio]r, 1787-1790., ADS. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - "A state of the case between Davies & Burks," signed by Nicholas Davies, 13 March 1790., ADS. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Accounts of William Cabell, 1790., ADsS. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - George Gilmer, Pen Park, to Col. William Cabell, Union Hill, Amherst, 5 June 1790., ALS. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - A list of land belonging to William Cabell, Jun[io]r., D. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Receipt, signed by George Gilmer, 2 Oct. 1790., ADS. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Receipts of William Cabell, 1791., ADsS. (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Jo[seph] Jo[nes] Monroe, to [?], 18 Oct 1791., ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
    Item is requesting a copy of a bill.
  - Jo[seph] Jo[nes[ Monroe, Charlottesville, to W[illia]m S. Crawford, Clerk of Amherst, 22 Dec. 1791., ALS. (Box-folder 3:5)
    Item concerns his plans to move his law practice to Amherst.
  - George Gilmer, Penn Park, to Col. William Cabell, 26 Jan. 1792., ALS. (Box-folder 3:6)